So I'm going to talk about trust,
إذن سأتحدّث اليوم عن الثّقة،
and I'm going to start by reminding you
و سأبدأ بتذكيركم بالرؤى
of the standard views that people have about trust.
المعيارية التي يمتلكها النّاس عن الثّقة.
I think these are so commonplace,
أظنّ أنّها شائعة جدّا،
they've become clichés of our society.
لدرجة أنّها أصبحت صيغا مبتذلة لمجتمعنا.
And I think there are three.
و أعتقد أنّ هناك 3 منها.
One's a claim: there has been a great decline in trust,
أوّلها ادّعاء كون أنّ هناك انخفاضا كبيرا في الثقة،
very widely believed.
العديد يعتقدون ذلك.
The second is an aim: we should have more trust.
الثّاني هو هدف. يجب أن يكون هناك أكثر ثقة.
And the third is a task: we should rebuild trust.
و الثّالث هو مهمة: علينا إعادة بناء الثّقة.
I think that the claim, the aim and the task
أظنّ أنّ الادعاء و الهدف و المهمة
are all misconceived.
كلّها قد أُسيء فهمها.
So what I'm going to try to tell you today
لذا ما سأحاول قوله لكم اليوم
is a different story about a claim, an aim and a task
هي قصة مختلفة عن ادعاء و هدف و مهمّة
which I think give one quite a lot better purchase on the matter.
أعتقد أنّها تعطي صورة أعمق للموضوع.
First the claim: Why do people think trust has declined?
الادعاء أوّلا: لماذا يعتقد النّاس أنّ الثقة قد قلّت؟
And if I really think about it on the basis of my own evidence,
و عندما أفكّر بالأمر من وجهة نظرنا الشخصية،
I don't know the answer.
لا أعرف الإجابة.
I'm inclined to think it may have declined
أميل إلى التّفكير في أنّ الثّقة قد نقصت
in some activities or some institutions
في بعض الأنشطة أو بعض المؤسسات
and it might have grown in others.
و ازدادت في أخرى.
I don't have an overview.
ليس لي نظرة شمولية.
But, of course, I can look at the opinion polls,
لكنني بالطبع أستطيع أن أعتمد على استطلاعات الآراء،
and the opinion polls are supposedly
التي من المفترض أن تكون
the source of a belief that trust has declined.
مصدر الاعتقاد بأنّ الثّقة قد نقصت.
When you actually look at opinion polls across time,
في الواقع، إن ألقيت نظرة إلى استطلاعات الآراء على مرّ السنوات،
there's not much evidence for that.
ما من أدلة على ذلك الادعاء.
That's to say, the people who were mistrusted
ما أقصده هو، الأشخاص الذين لم نكن نثق بهم
20 years ago,
منذ 20 سنة مضت،
principally journalists and politicians, are still mistrusted.
خاصة الصحفيّين و السياسيّين، لا نزال فاقدين الثّقة بهم.
And the people who were highly trusted 20 years ago
و الأشخاص الذين كنّا نثق بهم بشدّة منذ 20 سنة مضت،
are still rather highly trusted: judges, nurses.
لازلنا نثق بهم الآن: القضاة و الممرّضات.
The rest of us are in between,
بقيّتنا يقف في المنتصف،
and by the way, the average person in the street
و على فكرة، الشّخص العاديّ بالشّارع
is almost exactly midway.
يقع في النّصف بالضبط.
But is that good evidence?
لكن هل هذا دليل جيّد؟
What opinion polls record is, of course, opinions.
ما تسجّله استطلاعات الآراء هي بالطّبع آراء.
What else can they record?
ما الذي يمكنهم تسجيله أيضا؟
So they're looking at the generic attitudes
إنّهم ينظرون إلى السّلوكات الجينيّة
that people report when you ask them certain questions.
التي يبلّغ عنها النّاس عندما تطرح عليهم أسئلة معيّنة.
Do you trust politicians? Do you trust teachers?
هل تثق بالسياسيّين؟ هل تثق بالمعلّمين؟
Now if somebody said to you, "Do you trust greengrocers?
إن سألك أحدهم: "هل تثق بالبقّالين؟
Do you trust fishmongers?
هل تثق بباعة السّمك؟
Do you trust elementary school teachers?"
هل تثق بمدرّسي المرحلة الابتدائية؟"
you would probably begin by saying, "To do what?"
ستكون إجابتك على الأرجح: "لماذا؟"
And that would be a perfectly sensible response.
و ذلك السّؤال حسّاس جدّا.
And you might say, when you understood the answer to that,
و قد تقول بعد فهمك للجواب عن ذلك السّؤال،
"Well, I trust some of them, but not others."
"حسنا، أثق ببعضهم و البعض الآخر لا."
That's a perfectly rational thing.
وهو أمر منطقيّ جدّا.
In short, in our real lives,
باختصار، على أرض الواقع،
we seek to place trust in a differentiated way.
نحن نريد في امتلاك الثّقة بطريقة متباينة.
We don't make an assumption that the level of trust
نحن لا نفترض أنّ مستوى الثّقة
that we will have in every instance of a certain type
الذي سيكون عندنا في كلّ لحظة تجاه
of official or office-holder or type of person
موظّف عامّ أو أيّ شخص
is going to be uniform.
سيكون متماثلا.
I might, for example, say that I certainly trust
على سبيل المثال، قد أقول أنّني أثق بالتأكيد
a certain elementary school teacher I know
في مدرّسة مرحلة ابتدائية أعرفها
to teach the reception class to read,
لتدريس السنوات الأولى كيفية القراءة،
but in no way to drive the school minibus.
لكن لا أثق بها لقيادة حافلة المدرسة.
I might, after all, know that she wasn't a good driver.
ربّما السبب هو كوني أعرف أنّها ليست سائقة جيّدة.
I might trust my most loquacious friend
ربّما أثق في أكثر أصدقائي ثرثرة
to keep a conversation going
كي يحافض على سير محادثة ما،
but not -- but perhaps not to keep a secret.
لكن لا أثق به في حفظ سرّ.
Simple.
الأمر بسيط.
So if we've got those evidence in our ordinary lives
إذن إن كانت هذه الأدلّة من حياتنا اليومية
of the way that trust is differentiated,
تشير إلى أن ثقتنا متباينة،
why do we sort of drop all that intelligence
فلماذا نتخلّى عن تلك المعلومة
when we think about trust more abstractly?
عندما نفكّر بالثقة بمفهوم تجريديّ؟
I think the polls are very bad guides
أظنّ أنّ استطلاعات الرّأي لا تصلح كأدلّة
to the level of trust that actually exists,
لمعرفة مدى الثّقة الموجودة في الواقع،
because they try to obliterate the good judgment
لأنّها تحاول إلغاء الأحكام الجيدة
that goes into placing trust.
عندما يتعلّق الأمر بالثّقة.
Secondly, what about the aim?
ثانيا، ماذا عن الهدف؟
The aim is to have more trust.
الهدف هو كسب مزيد الثّقة.
Well frankly, I think that's a stupid aim.
بصراحة، أظنّ أنّه هدف غبيّ.
It's not what I would aim at.
شخصيّا لن أختار هدفا مشابها.
I would aim to have more trust in the trustworthy
بل كنت لأهدف للوثوق أكثر في الموثوق به
but not in the untrustworthy.
و عدم الوثوق في من لا يستحق الثّقة.
In fact, I aim positively to try not to trust the untrustworthy.
في الواقع، أهدف إلى عدم الوثوق في من لا يستحق الثّقة بطريقة إيجابية.
And I think, of those people who, for example,
أنا أفكّر بالنّاس الذين، على سبيل المثال،
placed their savings with the very aptly named Mr. Madoff,
وضعوا مدّخراتهم عند شخص كفؤ اسمه السيد مادوف،
who then made off with them,
و الذي سرقهم فيما بعد،
and I think of them, and I think, well, yes,
عندما أفكّر فيهم، حسنا أعتقد أنّ
too much trust.
ثقتهم به كانت مبالغا فيها.
More trust is not an intelligent aim in this life.
البحث عن مزيد الثّقة ليس هدفا ذكيّا في الحياة.
Intelligently placed and intelligently refused trust
وضع الثّقة في الموضع المناسب
is the proper aim.
هو الهدف الصّحيح.
Well once one says that, one says, yeah, okay,
و ما إن يفكّر المرء في الأمر سيقول
that means that what matters in the first place
أنّ هذا يعني أنّ المشكل في الأصل
is not trust but trustworthiness.
لا يتعلّق بالثّّقة بل بأحقية الثّقة.
It's judging how trustworthy people are
الحكم في كيفية كون النّاس جديرين بالثّقة
in particular respects.
في بعض الجوانب.
And I think that judgment requires us to look at three things.
و أظنّ أنّ الحكم يتطلّب منّا أخذ ثلاثة أشياء بعين الاعتبار.
Are they competent? Are they honest? Are they reliable?
هل هم أَكْفَاءٌ؟ هل هم نزيهون؟ هل يمكن الاعتماد عليهم؟
And if we find that a person is competent
و عندما نجد شخصا كفؤا
in the relevant matters,
في أمور ذات صلة،
and reliable and honest,
نزيه و يمكن الاعتماد عليه،
we'll have a pretty good reason to trust them,
سيكون لنا أسباب وجيهة للوثوق به،
because they'll be trustworthy.
لأنّه جدير بالثّقة.
But if, on the other hand, they're unreliable, we might not.
لكن في المقابل إن كان لا يمكن الاعتماد عليه، فلا نثق به.
I have friends who are competent and honest,
لي أصدقاء نزيهون و أَكْفَاءٌ،
but I would not trust them to post a letter,
لكنني لن أثق بهم في إرسال رسالة
because they're forgetful.
لأنّهم سريعو النّسيان.
I have friends who are very confident
لي أصدقاء أمناء جدّا
they can do certain things,
بامكانهم القيام ببعض الأمور،
but I realize that they overestimate their own competence.
لكنني اكتشفت أنّهم يبالغون بشأن مدى كفاءتهم.
And I'm very glad to say, I don't think I have many friends
و أنا سعيدة جدّا لقولي أنّه ليس لي عديد الأصدقاء
who are competent and reliable but extremely dishonest.
الأَكْفَاءٌ و الذين يمكن الاعتماد عليهم لكنهم غير نزيهين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If so, I haven't yet spotted it.
أو ربّما أنّني لم أتفطّن لوجودهم.
But that's what we're looking for:
لكن هذا هو ما نبحث عنه:
trustworthiness before trust.
أحقيّة الثقة قبل الثّقة نفسها.
Trust is the response.
الثّقة هي الإجابة.
Trustworthiness is what we have to judge.
أحقيّة الثّقة هي ما يجب الحكم عليه.
And, of course, it's difficult.
و بالطّبع فالأمر صعب.
Across the last few decades, we've tried to construct
خلال العقود الماضية، حاولنا إنشاء
systems of accountability for all sorts of institutions
أنظمة محاسبة في كلّ أنواع المؤسّسات
and professionals and officials and so on
و المهنيّين و الموظّفين الحكوميّين و غيرهم
that will make it easier for us to judge their trustworthiness.
ممّا يجعل الحكم على مدى جدارتهم بالثّقة سهلا.
A lot of these systems have the converse effect.
و العديد من هذه الأنظمة لها مفعول معاكس تماما.
They don't work as they're supposed to.
إنّها لا تعمل كما ينبغي.
I remember I was talking with a midwife who said,
أذكر أنّني تحدّث مرة مع قابلة قالت لي:
"Well, you see, the problem is it takes longer
"المشكل هو أنّ اكمال المعاملات الورقية للولادة
to do the paperwork than to deliver the baby."
يستغرق وقتا أكثر من عمليّة الانجاب نفسها."
And all over our public life, our institutional life,
طيلة حياتنا العامة و المؤسساتية،
we find that problem,
نحن نواجه ذلك المشكل،
that the system of accountability
كون نظام المحاسبة
that is meant to secure trustworthiness
يفترض به تأمين المصداقيّة
and evidence of trustworthiness
و أدلة الجدارة بالثّقة
is actually doing the opposite.
إلاّ أنّها تقوم بالعكس تماما.
It is distracting people who have to do difficult tasks,
إنّها تشتّت انتباه الناس المجبرين على القيام بمهام شاقّة،
like midwives, from doing them
مثل القابلات، و القيام بها
by requiring them to tick the boxes, as we say.
يتطلّب أن يعجبهم الأمر.
You can all give your own examples there.
تستطيعون كلّكم اعطاءنا أمثلة.
So so much for the aim.
لازلنا نتحدّث عن الهدف.
The aim, I think, is more trustworthiness,
أظنّ أنّ الهدف هو المزيد من الجدارة بالثّقة،
and that is going to be different
و أنّ الأمور ستختلف إن
if we are trying to be trustworthy
حاولنا أن نكون جديرين بالثّقة
and communicate our trustworthiness to other people,
و التّعبير عن جدارتنا بالثّقة للآخرين،
and if we are trying to judge whether other people
و إن حاولنا معرفة بين من هو جدير بالثّقة
or office-holders or politicians are trustworthy.
من أصحاب المكاتب أو السياسيين و غيرهم.
It's not easy. It is judgment, and simple reaction,
الأمر صعب. إنّ الحكم و ردّة الفعل البسيطة
attitudes, don't do adequately here.
و المواقف ليست كافية في هذه الحالات.
Now thirdly, the task.
ثالثا، المهمة.
Calling the task rebuilding trust, I think,
أعتقد أنّ وضع مهمة إعادة بناء الثّقة نصب أعيننا
also gets things backwards.
ستكون له نتائج عكسيّة.
It suggests that you and I should rebuild trust.
إنّها تقتضي منّي و منكم إعادة بناء الثّقة.
Well, we can do that for ourselves.
حسنا، نستطيع القيام بذلك لأنفسنا.
We can rebuild a bit of trustworthiness.
نستطيع إعادة بناء قليل من الجدارة بالثّقة.
We can do it two people together trying to improve trust.
قد يتمكن من ذلك شخصان يحاولان تحسين الثّقة بينهما معا.
But trust, in the end, is distinctive
لكن الثّقة في نهاية الأمر مميّزة
because it's given by other people.
لأنّها تُكتسب من الآخرين.
You can't rebuild what other people give you.
لا تستطيع إعادة بناء ما تكتسبه من الآخرين.
You have to give them the basis
عليك أن تعطيهم أساسا
for giving you their trust.
يبنون عليه ثقتهم لك.
So you have to, I think, be trustworthy.
عليك إذن أن تكون جديرا بالثّقة.
And that, of course, is because you can't fool
و ذلك بالطّبع لأنّك لا تستطيع خداع
all of the people all of the time, usually.
كلّ النّاس طيلة الوقت.
But you also have to provide usable evidence
لكن عليك أن توفّر أدلة كافية
that you are trustworthy.
على كونك جديرا بالثّقة.
How to do it?
كيف يتمّ فعل ذلك؟
Well every day, all over the place, it's being done
إنّه يحدث، كلّ يوم، في كلّ مكان
by ordinary people, by officials, by institutions,
من قبل أشخاص عاديّين، موظفين رسميّين، مؤسّسات،
quite effectively.
بطريقة فعّالة.
Let me give you a simple commercial example.
دعوني أعطيكم مثالا تجاريّا بسيطا.
The shop where I buy my socks says I may take them back,
المتجر الذي أشتري منه جواربي يقول أنّه مستعد لاستعادتها،
and they don't ask any questions.
و لا يطرحون عليك أيّ أسئلة.
They take them back and give me the money
إنّهم يستعيدونها مجدّدا و يعيدون لي أموالي
or give me the pair of socks of the color I wanted.
أو يعطونني أيّ جوارب أخرى أختارها.
That's super. I trust them
هذا رائع. أنا أثق بهم
because they have made themselves vulnerable to me.
لأنّهم وضعوا أنفسهم في حالة ضعف أمامي.
I think there's a big lesson in that.
أرى أنّ هناك درسا جيّدا هنا.
If you make yourself vulnerable to the other party,
عندما تكون في موقف ضعف أمام الطّرف المقابل،
then that is very good evidence that you are trustworthy
فذلك هو دليل جيّد جدا على كونك جديرا بالثقة
and you have confidence in what you are saying.
و تثق في ما تقوله.
So in the end, I think what we are aiming for
لذا في النّهاية، أظنّ أنّه ليس من الصّعب الوصول
is not very difficult to discern.
إلى هدفنا المنشود.
It is relationships in which people are trustworthy
إنّها العلاقات التي تكون فيها الأطراف جديرة بالثّقة
and can judge when and how the other person
و يستطيع كلّ طرف أن يحكم ما إن كان الآخر
is trustworthy.
جديرا بالثّقة أم لا.
So the moral of all this is,
إذا العبرة من هذا كلّه،
we need to think much less about trust,
أنّنا نحتاج إلى التّفكير أقلّ في الثقة،
let alone about attitudes of trust
و المواقف من الثقة التي ينقلها
detected or mis-detected by opinion polls,
لنا استطلاعات الرأي،
much more about being trustworthy,
بل يجب التفكير في كيف نصبح جديرين بالثقة،
and how you give people adequate, useful
و كيف نعطي الناس أدلة كافية بسيطة
and simple evidence that you're trustworthy.
عن كوننا جديرين بالثقة.
Thanks.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)